Paolo Tamagnini

paolotamag.github.io twitter.com/paolotamag

linkedin.com/in/paolo-tamagnini-2490433a

Data scientist with research experience, fond of interactive data visualization for complex problems, data evangelist in the open source space, aware of pros and cons of both scripting and UI-based ML platforms. **Keywords**: visual programming, visual analytics, data science, eXplainable AI, Python, KNIME, d3.js

## EXPERIENCE

### KNIME GmbH

Berlin, Germany

Email: paolotamag@gmail.com

Mobile: +39 333 496 4088

Senior Data Scientist, Evangelism Team

May. 2018 - present

- Building Data Science Apps via Visual Programming: At KNIME I am building back-end and front-end apps via the KNIME visual programming framework. Those apps are then adopted, customized and deployed by KNIME customers. Since May 2021 I have been leading a team of data scientists to build, verify, document and publish Verified Components. Sometimes scripting in JavaScript, Python and R is required. The apps I personally build are around those topics: guided/visual analytics, autoML, human-in-the-loop, MLOps, active learning, weak supervision and explainable/responsible AI.
- Evangelism via Articles, Conferences and Social Media: After a new app is made publicly available on KNIME Hub or an innovative KNIME feature is released, I work with my team to create contents on different formats for external and internal channels. For example our work is published on data science online magazines, business conferences, meetups and webinars. Find links on my my website or follow me on Twitter:)
- Supporting the KNIME Community: Given that KNIME Analytics Platform is free and open source many community members are also inspired by our work and share their own projects online. I am currently scouting, supporting and highlighting their work regardless of whether they are partners, customers or simply KNIME fans.
- Gartner Magic Quadrant and Forrester Wave: Each year I support the leadership team in preparing the briefings for external reports such as <u>Gartner</u> and <u>Forrester</u> which review and benchmark KNIME software in comparison with other vendors.

## New York University, Tandon School of Engineering

Brooklyn, NY

 $Research\ Intern$ 

Aug. 2016 - Nov. 2017

o Developing Machine Learning Applications in Python and JavaScript: Working as a research intern in the team of Prof. Enrico Bertini we developed two XAI tools Rivelo and a Python package partial\_dependence. I presented both of them at a Google NYC Research Seminar.

## **EDUCATION**

# Sapienza University of Rome

Rome, Italy

Two-year M.Sc. in Data Science; GPA: 4.00 (110 cum laude / 110)

Oct. 2015 - Oct. 2017

o The first master in Italy for data science: Studied topics were: machine learning, statistical and bayesian inference, cloud computing and more. Most of the projects were coded in *Python* or *R* and they are all uploaded to my <u>GitHub</u>. I graduated in October 2017 being part of the first graduation of data science in Italy with important guests from companies and institutions like Google, Eurostat, Unicredit and more.

## Sapienza University of Rome

Rome, Italy

B.Eng. in Management; GPA: 3.89 (107 / 110)

Oct. 2012 - Oct. 2015

• A bachelor covering basics of most scientific and business areas: This course helped me to find my love for data and taught me to be flexible to many different domains.

### Programming Skills

- Languages: Python, d3.js, R, SQL, HTML, CSS
- Tools: KNIME Analytics Platform, KNIME Server, quick learner of other workflow-based frameworks

#### Publications

• Interpreting Black-Box Classifiers Using Instance-Level Visual Explanations:

P. Tamagnini, J. Krause, A. Dasgupta and E. Bertini. In Workshop HILDA co-located with SIGMOD 2017.